Guide to the Alton Crane Melville family home movies 1940-1968
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Alton Crane Melville family home movies
1940-1968
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0655
Melville, Alton Crane
55 8mm films, 19 16mm films
The Alton Crane Melville family home movies (1940-1968) consist of footage of the Melville family's vacations, home life and special events across multiple generations. In addition to family footage of Alton and Verna Melville and their children, many of the films in this colleciton contain footage of competative or recrational skiing at resorts in Utah and around the world. Both Alton Crane Melville and his son, Marvin Melville are prominent members of the United States ski community, and many of the films in this colleciton contain footage of competative or recrational skiing at resorts in Utah, Intermountain West, and around the world.
Biographical Note
Alton Crane Melville (1904-1966) was an avid skier who once served as president of the National Ski Association (NSA), an organization now known as the United States Ski and Snowboard Association (USSA). His son, Marvin Melville (b. 1935), is an internationally decorated and respected skier. He skied for the Granite High School, University of Utah, 1958 United States Olympic Alpine, and 1960 International Ski Federation (FIS) ski teams. In 1959, Marvin Melville became the National Collegiate Athletics Association (NCAA) champion in downhill, slalom and combined ski events. After retiring from competition, he served a tour in the Army and then opened a ski school for young racers. Melville coached the 1964 Women's Olympic Ski Team and the University of Utah Ski Team. He was inducted into the Sports Hall of Fame in 1990.
The Alton Crane Melville family home movies (1940-1968) consist of footage of the Melville family's vacations, home life and special events across multiple generations. In addition to family footage of Alton and Verna Melville and their children, many of the films in this colleciton contain footage of competative or recrational skiing at resorts in Utah and the Intermountain West, and around the world, including footage of Marvin Melville's ski races and training. All films have been digitized and are available to view on DVD.
The majority of the collection is arranged chronologically.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the Alton Crane Melville papers (Accn 723) and photograph colleciton (P0933) and the Marvin A. Melville family home movies (A1128).
Skis and skiing--United States--History--Sources; Skis and skiing--Utah--History--Sources; Home movies; City and Town Life; Sports and Recreation; Moving Images; Moving images; Home movies and video
- Parades, 1940 July 04; 1940 July 19; 1941 July 04; 8mm film (Reel 1)
  East Millcreek Parade (July 04, 1940)Childrens Covered Wagon Parade (July 19, 1940)Glorious 4th Parade (July 04, 1941)This film also contains footage of a young Marvin Melville (approximately age 5) riding a donkey.
- Brighton, Aposhian scenic trip, Kanosh deer, Mesa Verde, Arches National Monument, 1940-1941; 8mm film (Reel 2)
  Various Melville family outings 1940-1941: Brighton on the 4th of July 1940. Here Marvin rode horseback for the first time.The next outing is an autumn scenic loop via Payson canyon and Nephi Canyon. The Melville family drives this loop with the Aposhian family in September of 1940.The next outing is a trip to Kanosh to hunt deer. After the Melville men finish hunting, they go to Aunt Ella Staples house for lunch with the rest of the family.The next outing is a trip to Mesa Verde. Alton points out on a map the rout that they will take to Mesa Verde then there are various shots of the five-car caravan that they travel in. On the way to Mesa Verde, they stop at Arches National Monument.
- Christmas, 1940-1942; 8mm film (Reel 3)
  1940 Christmas memories: The Melville family decorating the Christmas tree, opening gifts, and playing with their new toys.1941 Christmas memories: The Melville children bathing the night before Christmas, decorating the Christmas tree, Mrs. Vera Melville reading "The Night Before Christmas" to her children, and the kids going to bed. On Christmas morning, the Melville family opens their presents.1942 Christmas memories: The Melville children wrapping presents, making lists of presents for Santa; the children opening their stockings and presents.
- Airway parade, 1940-1942; 8mm film (Reel 4)
  Footage of the old Airway Buses and of the various places that the Melville family and friends went on them. Destinations include Jackson Lake in Grand Teton National Park, Las Vegas, Nevada, and an Alligator farm. At the end of this film there are several shots of the various transit systems in Salt Lake City including Airway Buses, Murray Cab, and the Salt Lake Trolley System (SLTS).
- Grandma Melville at 90 years old, Black Rock, Easter with bicycles, Knab, Zion National Park, Kanosh, Logan, 1940 July 18; 1940 September 06; 1942 April 05; 8mm film (Reel 5)
  Various trips that the Melville family went on in 1940 and 1942: The first of these trips is to Black Rock on July 18 1940.The second is a trip to Grandma Melville's birthday party at the Sorenson's home on September 6 1940 where four generations of this family can be seen all together.The third trip is to Kanosh where the Melville men hunt for deer. This film also contains footage from Easter day in 1942 when the Melville children are given bicycles.
- Bennions, Lagoon, Grandma at 87 years old, 1940 August-1945; 8mm film (Reel 6)
  The Melville adults diving and swimming at a family friend's swimming pool while the Melville children play with their grandfather. The Melville family visits the Bennion family in Taylorsville in August of 1940. Later, Marvin visits Grandmother Bennion at the old Hyrum Bennion home.In 1945 the entire Melville family visits with Grandma Bennion. This film ends with a family trip up Millcreek Canyon where they enjoy fried steak.
- Marie, 1941 January-August; 8mm film (Reel 7)
  Marie Melville, Marvin's little sister, as a newborn, at six months old, eight months old, and at a year and three months.
- Kids: birthdays, school, Alice in blue gown, Easter, 1941-1943; 8mm film Double exposed (Reel 8)
  Footage of the Melville children's birthdays, their first day of school, and the Melville family's Easter celebration. The first birthday celebration is on February 15 1941 for Marvin. The second birthday celebration is also in February of 1941 for Marvin's sister Marie.
- Jackson Hole, Weber Park, 1942; 8mm film (Reel 9)
  Melville family vacations to Jackson Hole and Weber Park: In Jackson Hole, the family camps at the Turpin Meadow Lodge. They go on various day hikes and one afternoon they go horseback riding to the South entrance of Yellowstone National Park. There is also footage of several black bears that they encountered during their visit.The trip to Weber Park includes scenic views, footage of the Melville children playing in a river, and various shots of the Chapel of Transfiguration.
- Neighborhood, zoo, Grandview Quartet, Sadie Hawkins dance, Movie Club, Mirror Lake, 1942; 1943 August 07; 8mm film (Reel 10)
  Various local activities that Alton Melville and his wife participated in. These activities include taking the children to the Zoo, playing card games with the neighbors, singing with the Grandview Quartet, going to a Sadie Hawkins dance, and playing bingo with the Movie Club. This film also contains footage of the Melville family's trip to Mirror Lake in 1943 where they hike, go horseback riding, and have a picnic.
- Farming, planting, Lu Ann, Daisy, Easter in Snake Valley, zoo, baby, Deer Creek, harvest, 1942-1944; 8mm film (Reel 11)
  A farmer farming, planting and harvesting his crops in 1944.Marvin's younger sister Lu Ann as a newborn baby. The Melville family goes to the zoo in Salt Lake City, to a horse jumping Home Show, to the Olympus Stables where a few men build a fence, and to Deer Creek in Heber Valley where they fish and swim.
- Delta, Petersens, Nebo Loop, deer hunt, winter, 1943-1944 January; 8mm film (Reel 12)
  Various trips that the Melville family went on in 1943 and 1944. These trips include a drive through Nebo Loop via Nephi Canyon and Payson Canyon, a trip to Delta, a deer hunting trip to Kanosh, and a trip to see a family friend's wedding. This film also contains footage of Thanksgiving Day in 1943 and various shots of the winter streets in January of 1944.
- Mirror Lake, 1944; 8mm film (Reel 13)
  The Melville family's camping trip at Mirror Lake in 1944. The footage includes various shots of the campground and cabin that they stayed in, the hikes that they went on, and of the children playing in the lake.
- Italians Pow-Cottams, Horace, Stan, fishing in American Fork Canyon, 1944; 8mm film (Reel 14)
  Footage of a soccer game hosted for military veterans and of a fishing trip in American Fork Canyon. Images of the fishing trip include horseback riding to the lake, fishing on the lake, cooking the fish, and scenic views.
- Airway, Denver, 1944; 8mm film (Reel 15)
  The Melville family's trip to Denver Colorado where they enjoy the natural surroundings of a lake, mountains and pine trees. There is a brief shot of the front page of a newspaper titled Hobo News. The headline, slightly cut off, reads Lets sink the rising sons of... The last several shots of this film are of two men walking along the train tracks.
- Wedding, 1944; 16mm film (Reel 16)
  Alton and Verna Melville's wedding: shots of guests and family mingling and of the receiving line.
- James A. Melville, Verna and Alton's wedding, 1926; 1944; 8mm film (Reel 17)
  The first part of this film is a copy of another film from 1926 that contains footage concerning the Deseret National Bank. The footage includes a view of the bank from the opposite corner of the street, a few shots of the main banking room on a regular workday, and of a directors meeting held on the seventh of December. There is a shot of each man present at the meeting with their name and title preceding their image. These men include James A. Melville, Edward Rosenbaum, John G.M Barnes, James A. Eldredge, H. H. Rolapp, M. S. Eccles, and R. Q. Cannon. The second part of this film documents Alton and Verna's marriage and consists of footage of the receiving line.
- Christmas, Bennion, Alta skiing, Nate Larsen, 1944-1945; 8mm film (Reel 18)
  The Melville family's 1944 Christmas celebration: This celebration consists of singing Christmas Carols as a family, opening presents and stockings, and gathering with extended family for dinner. Also in this film, the Melvilles go to Alta for a day of free skiing and to the Bennion's home where the two families enjoy the Holliday season together.
- Marie's birthday, Lu Ann's birthday, Alta: Lu Ann, 1945; 8mm film (Reel 19)
  Marie and Lu Ann Melville's birthday celebrations: The celebrations include playing games with friends, opening presents, and eating birthday cake. This film also contains footage of Lu Ann's first time going to Alta Ski Resort with the family.
- Green River Lakes, Manila, July 4th: Aposhians, rain, ducks, 1945; 8mm film (Reel 20)
  Various trips that the Melville family went on in 1945: The first is the Melville's trip to Wyoming where they visit the Fort Bridger Museum, the first school house in Wyoming, the old post office in McKinnel Wyoming, and the Green River Lakes area where they fish and enjoy the view. The second trip is to Manila Utah. This film also contains footage of the Melville's 4th of July celebration with the Aposhian family. This celebration includes a 4th of July picnic and parade.
- Christmas, 1946; 8mm film (Reel 21)
  1946 Christmas memories: These celebrations include a Christmas parade, decorating the house and Christmas tree, a man dressed in a Santa suit delivering presents and filling the stockings, and opening presents Christmas morning. Towards the end of this film, there is footage of "Winter Thrills" which consists of playing in the snow and going on a horse drawn sled ride.
- Lions Club, Cedar City, 1946 June 22; 8mm film (Reel 22)
  Lions Club Convention in Cedar City, Utah. The footage includes several shots of two billboards; the first sign reads Convention and the second sign reads Hudson Horse Show. This film also contains footage of the elephants in the circus, and various shots of the members of the Lions Club mingling outside.
- Skiing, Lu Ann's Birthday, Las Vegas, Cedar City, Yellowstone, school, 1946; 8mm film (Reel 23)
  The Melville family free skiing, celebrating Lu Ann Melville's birthday, traveling to Las Vegas, Cedar City, and Yellowstone National Park, and of the kids going to school: The footage of Lu Ann's birthday includes several shots of Lu Ann and Marie blowing out the candles on the cake, the family eating the cake and of Lu Ann opening her presents. The footage of the Melville's trip to Las Vegas includes several shots of the family in a boat on Lake Mohave. The footage of the Melville's trip to Cedar City includes several shots of a parade and of Marie and Lu Ann on a swing. The footage from Yellowstone National Park includes several shots of the Old Faithful Geyser, and of Alton, Marvin, and Marvin's friend fishing. The footage of the Melville kids going to school includes several shots of Marvin walking to school with his friends while Marie walks to school with her friends. Lu Ann is too young to go to school yet, so she waves goodbye to her siblings from the front porch.
- Air Circus, Joe Holland, Marie's birthday, Lu Ann, Utah Lake, 1946-1947; 8mm film (Reel 24)
  The Melville family's Sunday drive to see the Air Circus, of Marie's birthday, and of the Melville's trip to Utah Lake: The footage from the Air Circus includes several shots of various airplanes on the ground and in the sky. The footage of Marie's birthday includes several shots of Marie opening presents, blowing out the candles on her birthday cake, everyone having cake, and of Marie and her friends playing bingo. The footage of the Melville's day spent at Utah Lake includes several shots of the family putting the boat into the water and boating around the lake.
- Skiing, Jackson Hole, Wyoming, 1946 December; 1947 February; 8mm film (Reel 25)
  The Melville family skiing at Alta in December of 1946 The Melville's family trip to Jackson Hole Wyoming in February of 1947. They attend the Cutter Races and go skiing. At the end of this film, there are several shots of Alton Crane Melville with a broken ankle.
- Lions Club, Logan, Sorensens, USO, July 4th parade, 1947 June 20; 1947 July 01; 1947 July 04; 8mm film (Reel 26)
  The Melville family attending the Utah Centennial Regatta with the Lions Club. The Utah Centennial Regatta was held in Logan on June 20, 1947. The Melville family visiting with the Sorensen family on July 1, 1947 and of the 4th of July parades in Logan and in Salt Lake City.
- This and that, Main Street, Hotel Utah, 1947; 8mm film (Reel 27)
  Footage of the LDS Temple and of Main Street viewed from the roof of the Hotel Utah in 1947. There is also a shot of a street corner from an office window. This film also contains footage of Lu Ann Melville, Raymond, Bill Roger, and Eddie Schanhals. The remaining footage of this film contains images from a bomber plane exhibit.
- Millcreek Canyon, Nebo Loop, Taylorsville, Christmas, Salt Lake City Main Street, cat and dog with Spencer, Sun Valley, Brighton skiing, Lu Ann's birthday, 1947-1948; 8mm film (Reel 28)
  Various trips that the Melville family went on in 1947 and 1948. These trips include a day spent in Millcreek Canyon, a day spent driving the Nebo Loop, a trip to Taylorsville, and of the Melville's family trip to Sun Valley. In Millcreek Canyon, the family has a picnic, Lu Ann and Marie Melville collect leaves and swing on a nearby swing, and an unknown man paints the surrounding scenery in oil paints. The Sunday drive through Nebo Loop contains footage of the surrounding scenery and of the Melville family stopping for a picnic. The footage of the Melville's trip to Sun Valley contains footage of the family skiing, a list of lift ticket prices, and of a snow sculpture. This film also contains footage of Salt Lake City's Main Street in 1947, of the Melville family skiing at Brighton, and of their 1947 family Christmas celebrations. The footage of these celebrations contains images of the family Christmas shopping, visiting Temple Square to see the lights, and of Lu Ann and Marie Melville sitting on Santa's lap in downtown Salt Lake.
- Lions Club, St. George, 1948 June 02; 8mm film (Reel 29)
  The Melville's trip to St. George with the Lions Club. While in St. George, the group is seen dancing and singing along to an oboe and accordion, taking jeeps off-roading followed by a short hike to a scenic viewpoint, swimming, attending a formal occasion, and visiting the scenic view area in Zions National Park.
- July 4th and 24th, Easter, West Delta, 1948; 8mm film (Reel 30)
  For July 4th and July 24th, the Melville family goes to see the local parade. For Easter, the Melville children go on an Easter egg hunt. This film also contains footage of the Melville family's trip to West Delta where they drive around the town.
- Rosecrest groundbreaking, carnival, 1948 August 1-3; 8mm film (Reel 31)
  Rosecrest Groundbreaking ceremony (August 1, 1948). Rosecrest Ward Carnival (August 1-3, 1948). This carnival was sponsored by the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (LDS Church).
- Brighton, Deer Killed, Marie's Birthday, Taylorsville, 1949 January-February; 8mm film (Reel 32)
  Marvin and Marie Melville free skiing at Brighton. A deer who was killed. Marie's birthday. The Melville's trip to Taylorsville. The footage of Marie's birthday contains images of Marie opening presents and of her and her friends eating birthday cake. The footage of the Melville's trip to Taylorsville contains images of the family Nordic skiing and of Lu Ann and Marie Melville being pulled on a sled by a tractor.
- Brighton, Easter, Clayton, Deer Creek and Little Deer Creek, Mother's Day, Taylors in Provo, July 4th and 24th parades, trip to Monticello, 1949; 8mm film Parade footage is double exposed (Reel 33)
  The Melville family skiing at Brighton, of the Melville family's celebration of various holidays, of their trip to Monticello, and of the various White and Melville builders sites. The holidays celebrated in this footage include Easter, Mother's Day, July 4th and July 24th. For Easter, the Melville children go on an Easter egg hunt, and for the 4th and 24th, the family goes to the local parades. The footage of the Melville's trip to Monticello includes images of a geyser, of the surrounding scenery, and of their hike in Devils Garden. The White and Melville Builders sites include the Deer Creek Project and the L.D.C Project. There is an image of a sign that reads Thru 700 ft. of tunnel and a mile of pipe line, and images of a backhoe moving dirt.
- Yellowstone, Bears, 1949; 8mm film (Reel 34)
  The Melville family's trip to Yellowstone National Park: While in Yellowstone, the family hikes through the woods, goes fishing, visit the Old Faithful Geyser, and drives to the Upper Falls. Throughout this film, there is footage of various black bears including a mother bear and her cubs. At the very end of the film, there are a few shots of an elk in a field.
- Easter, deer hunt, Sorensens at Beau Brommel, family at 1300 East, Weilers, Hollands, addition to house, Christmas at Cottams, Jim Clayton, Taylorsville, 1949; 1955; 8mm film (Reel 35)
  Footage of the Melville family's 1949 Easter and Christmas celebrations as well as footage of Marvin hunting for deer with his father. This film also shows the Melville family leaving their home to visit their friends, the Sorensens, where all of the boys play basketball together. The Melville family then goes on a Sunday drive to Brighton where they go for a scenic ride on the ski lifts. This film also documents the Melville's addition to their home in 1955.
- Lions Convention, 1950 June 01; 8mm film (Reel 36)
  Lions Convention in Old Cove Fort which was used as a stop over point between Filmore, the first state cpital, and Beaver, sixty miles to the south. This stopping point was used freaquently by early settlers and was built in 1867.
- Brighton, Snake Creek, Telegram race, Snow Cup Races at Alta, 1950-1951; 8mm film (Reel 37)
  The Melville family skiing at Brighton and of Marvin racing in the Telegram races and in the Snow Cup Races at Alta. The footage of Brighton includes the family taking the "Utah Motor Tours" bus up Big Cottonwood Canyon to Brighton where they hike in single file up the hill then ski down. They also stop in the trees to cook their lunch over a small fire. The footage from the Telegram Races includes the races getting ready and skiing the course. The footage from the Snow Cup Races at Alta includes skiers getting on the chair lift, scenic views from the chair lift, the racers in the starting gate, and of the racers at the midpoint of the course.
- White and Melville, Water Tank on Wasatch Blvd., July 4th, Neffs Canyon, 1950-1952; 8mm film (Reel 38)
  The White and Melville water well on 3300 South and Wasatch Boulevard; men working on a water irrigation system. 4th of July Parade in Salt Lake City 1952. A trip to Neffs Canyon where the Melville family goes on a boat ride, and sees a black bear and a waterfall.
- Lions Vernal Convention, 1951; 8mm film (Reel 39)
  The Melville's trip to Vernal for the Lions Convention. Once in Vernal, the greetings and introduction are given and then everybody mingles with one another. After this, the group is seen feeding baby lambs from bottles.
- Jackson Hole, Winter Park: Colorado, 1951-1952; 8mm film (Reel 40)
  Marvin's 1951-1952 high school ski team's trip to Jackson Hole for a race. The footage from this race includes images of the racers getting ready, in the starting gate, and skiing the course. It is noted that Bonnie Jo is racer 46 and that Teniel H. is racer 48. This film also contains footage of a jumping competition held at the Winter Park in Colorado.
- Knudsen Cup, American Lecidn Races, Landes Jump, 1952; 8mm film (Reel 41)
  Marvin Melville skiing in the Knudsen Cup, the American Lecidn Races, and the Landes Jumping competition. The Knudsen Cup was held in Sun Valley Idaho and the footage of it includes Marie free skiing and Marvin and his fellow racers in the starting gate and in the course. The footage of the American Lecidn Races and the Landes Jumping competition includes several shots of various competitors jumping. It is noted that Marvin is competitor 2 in the Landes Jumping competition.
- Alta: Mt. Superior hike, Aspen: Roach Cup, Nationals, Sun Valley: Harriman Cup, Squaw Valley, 1952; 16mm film (Reel 42)
  The Melville family hiking Mt. Superior at Alta during the winter then skiing down. Marvin competing in the Roach Cup, Nationals, the Harriman Cup, and in a race in Squaw Valley. The Roach Cup was held in Aspen Colorado and consists of a giant slalom course, a slalom course, and downhill course. Nationals where also held at Aspen and consists of a giant slalom course, a slalom course, and downhill course. The Harriman Cup was held in Sun Valley Idaho and consists of a downhill course and a slalom course. The race in Squaw Valley also consists of a downhill course and a slalom course.